The Gilbert and Lila Silverman Fluxus Collection Archives
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
The Gilbert and Lila Silverman Fluxus Collection Archives
1900-2013 (bulk dates: 1952-1988)
The Museum of Modern Art. Museum Archives 11 West 53 Street New York, NY 10019-5497 Phone: (212) 708-9617 Fax: (212) 408-6385 Email: archives@moma.org
George Maciunas; Jon Hendricks; Gilbert Silverman
Approximately 200 linear feet 322 5" manuscript boxes 2 2.5" manuscript boxes 33 9.75 x 12.25" clamshell boxes 16 5 x 12" card boxes 14 15 x 12" record cartons 10 6 x 12" CD boxes 9 22 x 26" flat boxes 5 14.5 x 18.5" flat boxes 3 flat files 2 31 x 23" flat boxes 2 19.5 x 25.5" flat box 2 16.5 x 20.5" flat boxes 2 4.5 x 8" box 1 17 x 21" flat box 1 15 x 19" flat box 1 12 x 17.25" flat box 1 15.25 x 17.25" flat box 1 12 x 12 x 12" box 1 4.5 x 10" box 1 plastic binder
These papers comprise a portion of the Gilbert and Lila Silverman Fluxus Collection. (The rest of the collection is housed with the Department of Prints and Illustrated Books and the Museum's Library). The Silverman Collection was built and organized by scholar Jon Hendricks starting c. 1977, working with collectors Gilbert and Lila Silverman. It grew into one of the world's largest collections of artwork, documentation, and published materials related to Fluxus, an international network of artists based primarily in New York in the 1960s and '70s, and particularly to its founder, George Maciunas (1931-1978). These papers contain documentation, artifacts, and artworks gathered by Hendricks for the Collection, as well as the administrative records produced in the process. The collected records include correspondence between artists, ephemera, documentation of Fluxus plans and events, as well as much material from the studio/estate of George Maciunas. The created records include correspondence, exhibition loan files, publication files, and other administrative documents.
Historical Note
George Maciunas and Fluxus
George Maciunas (born 1931 Jurgis Mačiūnas in Kaunas, Lithuania; died 1978 in Boston, Massachusetts)artist, architect, designer, publisher, and consummate organizerwas the founder and guiding spirit of Fluxus.
Maciunas spent his early childhood in various sanatoria and homes for sickly children in Switzerland. When the Soviet army invaded Lithuania in 1944, the Maciunas family fled to Frankfurt am Main, Germany. In 1948 they were able to emigrate to the United States and settled in Levittown, Long Island. Maciunas studied graphic design and architecture at the Cooper Union School of Art from 1949 to 1952, and earned a postgraduate degree from there in 1953. He also studied architecture and music at the Carnegie Institute of Technology Pittsburgh from 1952 to 1954, earning a Bachelor of Arts in architecture in 1955. From 1955 to 1959, he studied art history at the Institute of Fine Arts, New York University. He would draw on these studies later during trips to Europe, sometimes with his mother, Leokadia Maciunas, with whom he remained exceptionally close throughout his life (his father, Aleksandras, died of cancer in 1954).
After brief employment as an architect, Maciunas worked as a graphic designer. In 1960, he opened the short-lived AG Gallery at 925 Madison Avenue with his friend Almus Salcius. It became an important exhibition and meeting space for the artists who would form Fluxus, though it closed the next year. Later in 1961, Maciunas moved to Wiesbaden, Germany under the employ of the United States Army, where, working as a designer and architect, he used his wages to fund the first Fluxus events.
The fundaments of Fluxus were rooted in the historical paradigms of Dada and the chance and indeterminate operations pioneered by composer John Cage. Originally planned by Maciunas in the early 1960s as a series of publications, Fluxus developed into an international network of artists active in the 1960s and '70s. Maciunas communicated with this network through frequent newsletters and mailings which would record Fluxus events and detail future plans. The activities of Fluxus, which centered around Maciunas as organizer of events and fabricator of artworks, focused primarily on the production and dissemination of artists' multiples and the presentation of festivals and concerts. Collective, performative, anti-institutional, and irreverent, many Fluxus artists sought to bridge the gap between different artistic media, as well as that between art and life.
The idea of Fluxus had already expanded beyond the printed page with the 1964 release of Fluxus 1, which was comprised of contributions from artists such as Ay-O, George Brecht, Shigeo Kubota, Ben Vautier, and La Monte Young. Fluxus's physical manifestations developed further into a series of "fluxkits," small artists' multiples contained in boxes. Maciunas would solicit ideas from artists and then design, fabricate, and distribute the kits. Maciunas also devoted himself from the early 1960s to a series of festivals and performance in both Europe and New York. Idealistic and ambitious, Fluxus was constantly evolving, with its various members often disputing Maciunas's self-asserted leadership (or, in turn, being "excommunicated" by him). Fluxus emerged as an uncompromisingly unique phenomenon, yet was also a vital component in the vibrant mix of conceptualism and performance that challenged established artistic paradigms in the 1960s.
History of the Collection
The Gilbert and Lila Silverman Fluxus Collection (here also referred to as the Collection) began in c. 1977, when real estate developer and art collector Gilbert Silverman, who already owned a work by Fluxus artist Geoffrey Hendricks (Sky and Two Pairs of Pants, 1967), noticed some pieces by that artist for sale on the street in New York outside the René Block Gallery. Artist Brian Buczak (then Geoffrey Hendricks's partner), who was selling the works, explained that he and other artists were trying to raise money for the medical expenses of their friend George Maciunas, whose ill health would cause his death the following year. $1,000, Buczak explained, would be recompensed with the same value in Fluxus works. Silverman assented to the proposal, but had not heard of Fluxus. Buczak therefore introduced him to Jon Hendricks.
Jon Hendricks, along with Barbara Moore, was at that time joint proprietor of a store called Backworks, which exhibited and sold, among other things, Fluxus objects and ephemera. Jon Hendricks, brother of Geoffrey Hendricks, introduced Silverman to the movement, and began helping him and his wife Lila to collect everything produced by Fluxus. This led to a series of important exhibitions and publications which are documented in Series VII: Silverman Administrative Files.
The goals and principles of their collecting are discussed in a statement by Jon Hendricks below in the Scope and Content Note. Hendricks collected materialartworks, documentation, and publicationsfrom artists and collectors the world over, and assembled them into a didactic collection, intended to illustrate the complete history of Fluxus.
For more information about the history of the collection, as well as Jon Hendricks's personal history, see IX.D.3 for a 2013 interview with Jon Hendricks.
Bibliography for historical note
Hendricks, Jon, ed.Fluxus etc.: The Gilbert and Lila Silverman Collection. Bloomfield Hills, Michigan: Cranbrook Academy of Art Museum, 1981.
Hendricks, Jon, ed.Fluxus Codex. Detroit, Michigan: Gilbert and Lila Silverman Fluxus Collection in association with H.N. Abrams, New York, 1988.
Kellein, Thomas.The Dream of Fluxus: George Maciunas, an artist's biography. London: Thames & Hudson, 2007.
Scope and Content
These records were collected and created by Jon Hendricks for Gilbert and Lila Silverman between c. 1977 and 2008, when the Collection was acquired by The Museum of Modern Art. They were intended to comprise, as nearly as possible, every work created by Fluxus and complete documentation of its activities. The Collection was built to tell, as fully as possible, the entire history of Fluxus; researchers interested in this are advised to begin with the Silvermans' many publications, from which they may determine a more focused course of research. This history is told through correspondence, ephemera, manuscripts, working material for projects, research conducted by Hendricks, and other documentation. Works of art are generally considered the province of the Department of Prints and Illustrated Books, and thus reside with the Museum Collection. (For more information about how objects were divided between the three departments, see "The Collection at MoMA" below.)
The Archive also contains a great deal of documentation related to specific artists, particularly in Series I: Artists, Personalities, and Groups; not all of this documentation is explicitly connected to Fluxus. Holdings are particularly significant for George Brecht, Ken Friedman, Dick Higgins, Milan Knžk, Arthur Kpcke, and Ben Vautier. Researchers specifically interested in George Maciunas will find a wealth of resources in Series V: George Maciunas Papers.
Researchers interested in the historiography of Fluxus, the work of Jon Hendricks, and twentieth-century art collecting in general will wish to consult Series VII: General Administrative Files, for documentation of the Collection's growth and its various projects.
The Collection at MoMA
While the entire Silverman Collection is considered as a single entity, the Museum acquired it with the knowledge that it would be divided among three departments for administrative purposes. The Museum Archives is responsible for documents and other archival records; the Department of Prints & Illustrated Books manages works of art (here taken to include performance photographs, audio and video recordings of performances, and event scores); and the Museum's Library oversees books and other published material.
Because the nature of Fluxus deliberately challenges the above classifications, the Museum's task upon acquiring the Collection was to decide how to divide and apportion it to best serve its preservation and access through research and exhibitions. After the Collection's arrival at MoMA in 2009, a series of cross-departmental meetings was held to determine which categories would be ideally served by each department. This project challenged the Museum's basic assumptions about what constitutes an artwork versus a document, and the importance of maintaining the multiple identities of objects that may be both. The actual work of sorting the materials and assessing individual cases was done throughout processing, with collaboration among the three departments. There are some exceptions to the divisions above. (When neccessary, works of art were generally kept in the Archive for reasons of preserving context, while documentary artifacts were transferred to the Department of Prints and Illustrated Books when their exhibition value was considered exceptionally high). Intellectually, the three parts of the Collection remain a single grouping.
Upon the acquisition of the Silverman Collection, Jon Hendricks was hired for a five-year period as Consulting Curator to assist with its cataloguing and processing, as well as to organize exhibitions.
Statement by Jon Hendricks regarding the genesis and development of the Silverman Collection
Jon Hendricks was asked by the archivist to prepare a statement about the creation of the collection:
The idea was to make a collection of a movement. It didn't start out that way. Initially Gilbert Silverman was interested in making a collection of Fluxus Editions. This fairly quickly gave way to a broader objective when some prototypes for Fluxus Editions, Fluxus publications, and posters and relics of Fluxus performance became available. Also it quickly became apparent that the traditional definitions of an artwork didn't apply to Fluxus. So like a spider and her web, flies and moths, insects of many sorts began to be attached to the net. "Art" vs. "not art" was not a criteria. What became a criteria was whether it was Fluxus or not. To us, a scrap of paper by George Maciunas with plans for a Fluxus concert or one with ideas for Flux Cabinet were just as important as finding a variant version of Jock Reynold's Potentially Dangerous Electrical Device, a Fluxus Edition. We made no distinction between letters by George Maciunas to Fluxus artists, and photographs of Fluxus performances by Bruce Flemming; between drawings by Arthur Kopcke and scores by George Brecht; big or small, fragile or durable, as long as something was Fluxus or directly related to Fluxus, we considered adding it to the collection. My idea was to try to gather as much material as possible, so that in the future, people could look at the movement from many angles, many points of view, and arrive at a notion of what the movement was about. I would use the word "triangulate" to describe my intent. The Silvermans were always supportive in this, rarely deciding not to acquire something that I would recommend, and in fact, they added many very important pieces to the collection from their own searchingsmaterial of Hi Red Center; numerous pieces of Milan Knizak, Joe Jones, George Brecht, Takako Saito and many more. To me, correspondence, photographs, notations, newspaper clippings, sound recordings, film, notebooks, scores, sketches, posters, flyers, programs, newsletters, journals, editions, constructions, relics, were all essential parts of the collection. They all formed a part of the Fluxus movement and were the "Art", are the art.
What was not collected for the most part were non-Fluxus works by Fluxus artists; material created, or documenting activities after George Maciunas' death in 1978; material of not Fluxus groups and artists who parallel Fluxus, but there are a number of exceptions. We have extensive material of the Aktual group and Milan Knizak; Arthur Kopcke and the gallery Kopcke; Dick Higgins and the Something Else Press; Japanese avant-garde especially Kunihara Akiyama and Toshi Ichiyanagi's graphic score show; Willem De Ridder's activities in Amsterdam beyond the European Mail Order Warehouse/Fluxshop; Ben Vautier, Art Totale and Laboratoire; Knud Pedersen, Yoko Ono, George Maciunas and more.
Gilbert Silverman would always advise "Focus!" In other words, don't get sidetracked by material that had little relationship to Fluxus. The possibilities were too vast and frequently very tempting.
We organized the collection in several logical and functional ways, unencumbered by notions of "Art" and "not Art"; "archival" and "works". First, material was arranged by artists, and Fluxus Collective, or group pieces Alocco to Zazeela and Fluxus Collective. Then, the performance material was organized by date and event:
June 9, 1962, Kleinen Sommerfest, Galerie Parnasse, Wuppertal to May 13, 1978 Flux Funeral for George Maciunas, 80 Wooster Street, New York City.
We maintained Artists Files A to Z, and collection files about purchases, exhibitions, and correspondence related to the collection. Some material was stored by medium or subjects:sound tapes and films, Fluxhouse cooperatives, photographic negatives, George Maciunas correspondence, George Maciunas' working material to assemble Fluxus Editions, the Library, Flat Files, small three dimensional objects. Then there were materials gathered together for projects that we were working on:scores and notations and related material for a planned two-volume work as a companion to the Fluxus Codex;George Maciunas' photographic work for a planned exhibition to be curated by Benjamin Buchloh;Fluxhouse Cooperatives for a book being worked on. There was material that was being kept together that needed to be catalogued and re-filed, especially material from George Maciunas' Estate; purchases from Harry Ruhé, Gallery 360?, John Hunov, Knud Pedersen, Jonas Mekas, Monika Kinley, Billie Maciunas, Finn Falkersby, Tut Kopcke, Hans Hartmann's Estate, etc. We also attempted to have multiple copies of printed material and Fluxus Editions for exhibitions so that the core collection would remain intact.
We attempted to cooperate with other institutions who have large holdings of Fluxus, supporting Simon Anderson's early work cataloging the Fluxshoe and David Mayor Archives at the Tate; joining with the Staatsgalerie Stuttgart in the joint purchase of George Maciunas' Estate; cooperating in many ways with Jean Brown and her Archive; with Hans Sohm before he sold his collection to Stuttgart; visiting and advising the Getty Center; giving photographic and other material to Rene Block's Fluxus in Deutschland exhibition; giving a George Maciunas Fluxus Kabinet to the Contemporary Art Center in Vilnius, Lithuania; giving small representative Fluxus collections to the Israel Museum, Jerusalem, and the Detroit Institute of the Arts, among a number of other associations.
We also loaned Fluxus works to numerous exhibitions around the world; opened the collection to many scholars for research; and published several books and catalogues on Fluxus and the collection including Fluxus, etc.;Fluxus, etc. Addenda I;Fluxus, etc. Addenda II;Fluxus Codex;What's Fluxus? What's Not! Why.;Fluxus Scores and Instructions.
Our intention was that the Gilbert and Lila Silverman Fluxus Collection would be a working collection, a shared collection, a learning collection and not a static repository. Our hope was that it would grow and be used, that it would shed light on this very radical and important 20th century international art movement, and that people would understand and respect the very central and important role that George Maciunas played in it. Gilbert and Lila Silverman and I feel that George Maciunas was a genius, and that it was he who conceived of the movement, shaped it, led it, held it together, defined its goals and ultimately gave his life to it.
Jean Brown once told me: "I was very fortunate to have known two geniuses in my lifeMarcel Duchamp and George Maciunas."
Jon Hendricks August 2, 2012
Photocopies
Photocopies created by the Collection (for both preservation and refiling purposes) appear throughout the material. These copies are usually, but not always, marked as such. As Maciunas used photocopy as a distribution medium, what Hendricks calls "vintage" photocopies should be considered original multiples, but are not always easily distinguished from mere copies. Researchers should take note of this when encountering photocopies.
Silverman numbering systems and inventory sheets
The Silverman Collection used three numbering systems consecutively. The first system, in which works were given "Silverman" numbers, is explained on page 29 of the Fluxus Codex:
"Some years ago, when we were preparing Fluxus etc. the Gilbert and Lila Silverman Collection for publication by The Cranbrook Academy of Art Museum [in 1981], it seemed sensible to attach a number to the works included in the catalogue. The book was arranged alphabetically by artist, with works within sections listed chronologically. Collective works, such as Fluxkit, were included in a section titled Fluxus, with periodicals and performance documents coming toward the end of the book.
As more works were added to the collection, it was necessary to expand the Silverman numbers based on the original system as follows:
>100.I = the new catalogue entry that comes chronologically after Silverman No. 100.
<100.I = the new catalogue entry that comes chronologically before Silverman No. 100.
<100.II = the entry which falls between Silverman No. 100 and No. 101 but follows >100.I.
<100.Ia = a new catalogue entry either identical to or a slight variant of <100.I.
>100.101 = work of an artist not in Fluxus Etc."
The second numbering system, initiated c. 1989 along with an appraisal of the collection, was intended to assign a 5-digit "inventory" number, which was included on an "inventory sheet" for each object. As a result, many objects have more than one type of number. Around 1991, when the appraisal project was no longer deemed necessary, the inventory numbers were discontinued in favor of a third system.
In the third and final numbering system, numbers were based on accession. New acquisitions were designated by the year and sequence of their acquisition. (For example, the fourth object or group of objects acquired in 1995 would be given the number 95.4. Sometimes the individual objects comprising a single purchase were further numbered: 95.4.1, 95.4.2, and so on.) It appears that these numbers were retroactively applied to some acquisitions made prior to 1991. This system was still in use when the collection was acquired by MoMA.
Numbers of all three types can be found written on objects or slips of paper near objects throughout the collection. Such numbers may correspond to an inventory or accession sheet containing information about the object's creation and provenance. These sheets may contain substantial, or alternately, very little information about an object, including artist, title, medium, provenance, and notes by Hendricks. When these sheets remained with the objects, the archivist left them for the researcher's benefit. When an object is labeled with an inventory number but no sheet is present, the researcher may assume that it corresponds to an inventory sheet. In order to allow researchers to find these sheets, these numbers have been included in the folder description where apparent. Square brackets around a number indicate that there is a photocopy of that object in the folder, rather than the original. For copies of specific inventory sheets, researchers may contact the study center of the Department of Prints and Illustrated Books. Inventory sheets were also sometimes used for objects acquired under the subsequent "accessions" system.
While the Silverman and inventory numbers appear to have been applied consistently, the accession numbers are not entirely consistent. Some accessions files are missing, and occasionally the same number was applied to two separate purchases.
Notes by Jon Hendricks
Notes by Jon Hendricks are scattered throughout the collection, and are not usually noted in the description unless they are of particular importance. Many concern the provenance of materials or notes about their use in Silverman publications and exhibitions.
Arrangement
The Gilbert and Lila Silverman Collection Archive was arranged by the archivist into ten series, with additional subseries divisions. Series I-VI and X primarily contain material collected by the Silverman Collection, while series VII-XI were primarily created by it. The material had been stored in multiple locations and was not well ordered when it arrived at MoMA, necessitating significant arrangement by the archivist.
The ten series are as follows:
Series I: Artists, Personalities, and Groups
Series II: George Brecht Notebooks
Series III: Dick Higgins Scrapbooks
Series IV: Event Files
Subseries IV.A: Event and Exhibition Ephemera
Subseries IV.B: Event Files
Series V: George Maciunas Papers
Subseries V.A: Correspondence
Subseries V.A.1: Original Correspondence from George Maciunas
Subseries V.A.2: Photocopy Correspondence to and from George Maciunas
Subseries V.B: Working Files
Subseries V.B.1: Working Files
Subseries V.B.2: Working Files Acquired from Nijole Valaitis
Subseries V.C: Studio Boxes
Subseries V.D: Art History Notes
Subseries V.D.1: Index Cards
Subseries V.D.2: Large Note Cards
Subseries V.D.3: Other Notes and Cards
Subseries V.D.4: Photocopies of Notes
Subseries V.D.5: Microfilm
Subseries V.E: Calendars
Subseries V.F: Fluxus Newsletters, Mailings, and Texts
Subseries V.G: Design Work: Fluxus and Personal
Subseries V.H: Design Work: Commercial and Other Projects
Subseries V.I: Personal and Family Material
Series VI: Fluxhouse Cooperatives
Subseries VI.A: Material Organized by Building
Subseries VI.B: Various